In the previous lesson we learned about generics and in this lesson we're going to be looking
at something that's called map types. So let's just remove the code from the previous
lesson and let's continue. So we're going to be looking at maps types which is another
powerful feature in TypeScript and map types let's us transform existing types into
new ones so that sounds pretty cool. So you can use it whenever you want to make
every property operational or lock them as read only or perhaps just to extract a
few keys. So this is exactly what map types is used for and it gives you that
control. I actually find map types and we're going to be looking at each of
these in a turn. So map types take as I said an existing type and creates a new
version by applying a certain transformation to the properties. Think of it a
little bit like a filter or perhaps a modifier for object shapes. So let's
first of all let's have a look at the partial map type. So the partial map
type makes all properties in a type optional. Let's just do an example let's
have a type of user, user's going to have an IIT property and also a name
property. So we can create a type and we can call it perhaps partial user.
The partial user and then we can use the partial keyword and we say partial user.
Next in order to use this we can actually create an actual object. So we do
consts say updates user and this is a type of partial user and because we define
as a partial it's basically allowing us to only provide certain properties. So
if we provide a name property let's say name or Alice and then the IIT is
effectively optional. Okay so that's why the type script is not complaining because
we defined it as a partial object. Of course we didn't actually define as a
partial we just had consts let's say another user and we just said that is a
type of user then of course if we come into here and we say name Alice it's
going to complain because we're not actually specifying the IIT. So that's
exactly why we use the partial because we know if we're doing an update then
perhaps we're not really interested in the IIT we're just wanting to update the user.
So this is exactly why we could use the partial keyword for things like API's
because in the API call we're going to provide the ID that we're going to
update. So we don't need to provide the ID in the actual object itself because
we just want to apply the properties that we want to update in this case maybe
we want to just update the name or if we wanted to have for example a phone
number let's have the phone number of string then we could actually come in here
and just say I also want to update the phone number to whatever it's going to
be. Now the next map type we can look at is required I'm just going to remove
this and come up an example. So the required is the name to just makes all
properties required even ones that weren't optional. So we're modifying our
object and we're kind of overriding the optional part we're saying the
optionals now need to become required. So let's say we have a type of
settings and we have a theme and optional theme which we do with the
question mark and also have say notifications notifications and they are
optional as well and then we come into here and we say type strict settings
and we want these to be required so required and then we provide the type so
required settings and now if it provides or create an object so it
const config and this time these are strict settings then it's going to
immediately complain and ask us to require properties so we're going to set
this to say dark and then notifications going to set to drew and then that then
satisfies TypeScript and it's happy that all the roads have been
accepted with values. The next one to look at is readoni so this pretty much
locks or properties so they can't be reassigned so let's just do an example so
you can see what that means so let's have a type or product and the product I do
string and price say number but come up come up to that let's do an ID and set
up a string and then price could be number right so we're going to create a
type of say frozen product this is going to have the readoni map type of type
product and then let's do something like book this is of type frozen
product set the ID to something like beaky beaky beaky beaky beaky zero zero
one price set to 1999 and now what happens is if we try to
update that price let's set it to 24 99 it's going to complain because we are
trying to change the number on a read only property and of course if it wasn't
frozen product but that was instead product then it would allow us to update
the price so when might you use readoni and just pretty good for creating
various constants or perhaps snapshots of data or any times you don't want to
change data any immutable data now we can move on we've had a look at three let's
now have a look at the fourth one which is pick the ick so this pick allows us
to create a brand new type by selecting specific keys Roman existing type so
that might sound a bit confusing so let me show you what I mean if we have a
type of user set up the properties again ID string name string and email
string let's have a type and it's going to call it public profile and that's
going to utilize two of the actual properties from this user we don't want to
three just want to so you can say pick user and then we specify the properties
that we want so we want name and use the pipe symbol so email so these are the
two properties we want to be specified so now if you come and create an
object of const profile and that's all type public profile we hover over it
it's going to expect us to supply those two properties we defined name and
email so of course we're going to do name Alice and email whatever it is then
it of course it's going to satisfy that so we can use the pick and if you
obviously want them to use APIs and we only want to update perhaps we have a
large object and we want to then create an update version of that large
object with just a certain number of properties like this example where we
are creating a profile we might only want to update the name and the email we
don't want to put updates or change the ID or other sensitive parts of the
profile that we've already set so we can use this to expose pretty much safe
all relevant fields as I said okay so that's the fourth one and the last one
we want to look at is record so record like this so this record allows us to
create a type with keys K and the values of type T so we are kind of using
generics here so we don't actually necessarily specify in the type up front so
again this is best explained to an example so let's have a type of role and
we have a role of admin editor and viewer and set up another type type of
permissions permissions and for this I want to use record using the type role but
rather than being string I want to set it as a boolean so this is going to be
kind of fun right let's see how this works so it creates an access object using
type of permissions I'm going to set the admin to true editor to true and the viewer to false
okay so we're getting some lines here and it looks like it's picking up
permissions not just from our playground what we have here but also actually
defined in TypeScript or other places as well so we can just change this from
permissions to our permissions and that goes away and just update this to
our permissions that's a trouble by using a playground is you often get
and kind of errors that not actually got nothing to do with the code and just
something to do with the environment itself now our actual errors have gone
away you can see what we're trying to do here we're creating some string
roles admin editor and viewer and then we are kind of wanting to set them
as perhaps access permissions or something like that
and we actually just defined the the actual objects or the the properties
and we're then actually specifying as the roles of the person
so admin is going to Boolean edit is Boolean and viewer is Boolean so they're
kind of acting as flags okay so let's have a quick wrap-up so
set them up types and our five of them let us reshape existing types
with precision we've learned how to make our properties optional
we've also learned how to make them required
we've touched upon read only how to use select using pick
and also now we've this record basically mapped
next up we're going to learn how to do conditional types which is
how to make types behave differently based on logic